Guide to the Violet Trefusis Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
- Writings, 1940-1956; Series II; 1.15; (2.75 boxes)
  - OTHER WRITINGS
    - Untitled description of Gaston Palewski and Paul Reynaud, holograph [in an unidentified hand?] (Box 4, Folder 114)
    - Untitled description of Louise de Vilmorin, typescript carbon, corrected, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 115)
    - Notes, holograph and typescript, incomplete (Box 4, Folder 115a)
- Additional Materials, 1924-1939; Series III; 0.1; (.25 box)
  - Miniature oval portrait [watercolor?] of Violet Trefusis as a child, in a case, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 116)
  - Photographs, 1932-55, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 116a)
    - François Dupré with the Princesse de Polignac, [1932]
    - Violet Trefusis with Osbert Sitwell, 1932, 1965
    - Sir Harold Acton, 1970
  - Photograph album containing snapshots taken at L'Ombrellino, 1924-39
    For a list of names of individuals appearing in the album, see the Appendix. A more detailed list of each photograph is included in the box with the album
- Oversize, 1; (1 box)
  - Photograph album containing snapshots taken at L'Ombrellino, 1924-39 (Box 5, Folder 117)
- Restricted Fragile, 0.2; (1 box) + 1 portfolio
  Conditions Governing Access
  Restricted fragile material. Reference surrogates have been substituted in the main files. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
  - Box 4, folder 116 (Box 6, Folder 118)
  - Box 2, folder 39 (Box port, Folder 119)
  - Box 4, folder 72 (Box port, Folder 120)
  - Box 4, folder 95 (Box port, Folder 121)
- January 2003 Acquisition, 1919-1955; Series IV; 0.21; (1 box)
  The January 2003 Acquisition primarily contains letters written to Violet Trefusis, including a letter from Denys Trefusis with a photograph of him enclosed. All letters are to Violet Trefusis unless otherwise indicated. Some third party correspondence is also included, as are two lists of books kept by Violet's friend Gilone (Princesse de) Chimay during the war, with Violet's autograph notes. Most of the material included in this acquisition is in French.
  Immediate Source of Acquisition
  Purchased from Bertram Rota Ltd. on the Starling W. Childs Library Fund, 2003.
  - Autograph letter from Denys Trefusis regarding their impending marriage, with a photograph of Denys, 1919 (Box 7)
    Arrangement
    Arranged in no particular order.
  - Permission for Violet to travel to England to flee German invaders, 1940 June 21
  - Autograph letter, signed, from "Jean" regarding war conditions, 1940 May 26
  - Autograph letter from an unidentified friend, possibly the Duchesse D'Harcourt, 1941 March 5
  - Autograph letter, signed, from "Colin", 1941 August 11
  - Autograph letter from an unidentified sender regarding a sea voyage in West Africa and residents of the region, undated
  - Autograph letter from an unidentified sender, undated
  - Autograph letter from an unidentified sender, 1942 December 4
  - Three autograph letters from "P.H." regarding social matters, undated
  - Typed letter, signed, to Cyril Connolly from Peter De Mendelssohn stating that the story by Violet Trefusis in the June issue of Horizon magazine is a "little masterpiece", 1943 June 19
  - Two lists, one manuscript and one typed, of books kept by Violet's friend Gilone (Princesse de) Chimay during the war, with autograph notes by Violet, 1940 June 2
  - Typed letter to "Madame Ia Duchesse" concerning a cache of silver owned by Violet that had been hidden from the Germans during the war by the Duchesse D'Harcourt, 1946 June 30
  - Typed letter, signed, from "Sylvia" from the Beekman Tower, New York City with manuscript corrections and notes, including a quotation from Sappho, 1946 July 17
  - Four autograph letters, signed, from Violet's suitor, Marchese Guido Sommi Picenardi, 1947 January
  - Autograph letter, signed, from Dorothy Heneage, expressing sadness due to Violet's mother's approaching death, 1947 May 24
  - Autograph letter, signed, from 'Tony" (Done Antonio De Gandarillas) concerning Violet's mother's death, 1947 September 17
  - Eleven autograph and typed letters, signed, from Betty Batten concerning social matters, mutual friends, including Nancy Mitford, and Violet's character, 1945-1953
  - Autograph letter, signed, from Frank Ashton-Gwatkin, from the Royal Institute of International Affairs, London, [1955?] October 6